Guide to the George Mueller collection on the Cook-Folsom Expedition
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
George Mueller collection on the Cook-Folsom Expedition
1894-1979
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Cook, Charles W., 1839-1927; Chesnut, V. K. (Victor King), 1867-1938; Mueller, George D., 1921-2016
2717
0.2 linear feet one box, one oversize folder
Grandson of C. W. Cook and Montana historian. Materials accumulated by Mueller on the Cook-Folsom Expedition.
Collection is open for research.
George Donald Mueller was born in Lewistown, MT, in 1921 to Oscar and Josephine Mueller. He graduated from Fergus County High School, attended Montana State College for two years, then joined the Army and served in World War II. After completing his education, he became a meteorologist with the U.S. Weather Service in Meacham, OR, and Great Falls, MT. He returned to Lewistown after retirement.
Mueller was vitally interested in local and state history. He was active in the Central Montana Historical Association, the Sons and Daughters of the Montana Pioneers, and was a member of the Montana Historical Society. His articles were published in a number of publications, including the Montana Magazine of Western History.
As the grandson of Charles W. Cook (who, along with David E. Folsom and William Peterson, made up the Cook-Folsom-Peterson Expedition of what is now Yellowstone National Park in 1869), Mueller was especially dedicated to the stewardship of Cook's memory and to ensuring that his role in the Park's development was recognized.
He died in 2016 at the age of 94.
Materials accumulated by George Mueller, grandson of Cook, on the Cook-Folsom Expedition. The collection includes a copy of the Cook-Folsom diary manuscript as written by Chestnut; a typescript of the Cook-Folsom diary; Cook's remarks on the Park's 50th anniversary; correspondence with J.E. Haynes, V.K. Chestnut, Park personnel, Horace Albright, Aubrey Haines, Calvin Coolidge, and Joseph Dixon; and photographs of Cook and others, mostly taken for the Park's 50th anniversary.
Gift of Sally Mueller, along with her siblings Ruth Mueller and Glenda Christenson, on behalf of the George Mueller Estate, 2022.
Cook, Charles W., 1839-1927
United States--Discovery and exploration; Yellowstone National Park--Discovery and exploration
Explorers--United States; Explorers--Yellowstone National Park
National Parks; Expeditions and Adventure; Wyoming; Montana
Diaries; Correspondence; Photographs
- Folsom manuscript, Chesnut copy (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cook-Folsom diary typescript (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Folsom-Cook Expedition, printed copy, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Press release on C.W. Cook (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cook's remarks on the 50th anniversary of Yellowstone National Park, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with J. E. Haynes, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence with V. K. Chesnut, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence with Yellowstone National Park, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence with Horace Albright, 1923-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with Aubrey Haines, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter from Calvin Coolidge, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from Joseph Dixon, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 50th anniversary photograph, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- William Peterson photos (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Portrait of Charles Cook (Folder-os 1)